Guide to the Thomas Irwin Emerson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1947-1987; Series III
  The series includes articles, reviews, speeches and book drafts written by Thomas Emerson. Writings are separated into two groups: Articles and shorter writings and Books. In keeping with the original order of the collection, some of Emerson's articles and shorter writings are arranged alphabetically while the majority are arranged chronologically. Materials relating to Emerson's books are arranged alphabetically by book title.
  - Articles and shorter writings
    - Alphabetical
      - "Academic Freedom of the Faculty Member as Citizen", 1963-1965 (Box 82, Folder 1)
      - "Affirmative Side of the First Amendment", 1981-1982 (Box 82, Folder 2)
      - "Bill of Rights Today", 1980, 1983, undated (Box 82, Folder 3)
      - "Bureaucracy and Democracy", 1977-1980, undated (Box 82, Folder 4)
      - "Citizen's Right of Access to Information", 1984 (Box 82, Folder 5)
      - "Civil Liberties" and "Freedom of Speech" [entries in the Encyclopedia of the American Constitution ], 1979-1985, undated (Box 82, Folder 6 - 7)
      - "Civil Liberties, Government Authority, and Democracy: The American Experience", 1982-1983 (Box 82, Folder 8)
      - "Communication and Freedom of Expression", 1972-1973 (Box 82, Folder 9 - 10)
      - "Control of the Intelligence Agencies", 1983, undated (Box 82, Folder 11 - 12)
      - "Court v. the Demonstrators", 1966-1967 (Box 82, Folder 13)
      - David Glass Memorial Lecture, 1981-1982 (Box 82, Folder 14)
      - "Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Bill of Rights", 1971-1972, undated (Box 83, Folder 15 - 16)
      - "First Amendment in the Year 2000", 1978-1979, undated (Box 83, Folder 17)
      - "First Amendment Rights and the Burger Court", 1979-1980 (Box 83, Folder 18)
      - "Freedom of the Press Under the Burger Court", 1978-1983 (Box 83, Folder 19)
      - "Government Secrecy and the Citizen's Right to Know", 1977-1979 (Box 83, Folder 20)
      - Guide to American Law [offers to write subject entries], 1980, 1983 (Box 83, Folder 21)
      - James, Fleming memorial, 1972-1981, undated (Box 83, Folder 22)
      - "Justice Douglas' Contribution to the Law: The First Amendment", 1974, 1980, undated (Box 83, Folder 23)
      - "National Security and Civil Liberties", Undated (Box 83, Folder 24)
      - New York Compass articles, 1950 (Box 83, Folder 25)
      - "Pornography and the First Amendment: A Reply to Professor MacKinnon", 1984 (Box 83, Folder 26)
      - "Power of Congress to Change Constitutional Decisions of the Supreme Court: The Human Life Bill", 1981-1982 (Box 83, Folder 27)
      - "State of the First Amendment on the Eve of 1984", 1983-1985 (Box 83, Folder 28)
      - University of Connecticut law school commencement address, 1985 (Box 83, Folder 29)
    - Chronological
      - 1947-1958 (Box 84, Folder 30 - 40)
      - 1960-1970 (Box 85, Folder 41 - 49)
      - 1971-1976 (Box 86, Folder 50 - 56)
      - 1977-1980 (Box 87, Folder 57 - 63)
      - 1981-1986, undated (Box 88, Folder 64 - 71)
  - Books
    - Political and Civil Rights: A Collection of Legal and Related Materials
      - Book drafts
        - 1949 (Box 89, Folder 72 - 81)
        - 1951 (Box 90, Folder 82 - 91)
        - Undated (Box 91, Folder 92 - 97)
      - Contracts, 1967-1975 (Box 91, Folder 98 - 99)
      - Correspondence, 1948-1951, 1970-1987 (Box 91, Folder 100 - 102)
      - Permissions to reprint from other works, 1966-1967 (Box 91, Folder 103)
      - Promotional material, Undated (Box 91, Folder 104)
      - Reviews, 1952-1972 (Box 91, Folder 105 - 106)
      - Sales, 1957-1985 (Box 92, Folder 107 - 109)
      - School adoption reports, 1968-1978 (Box 92, Folder 110)
    - System of Freedom of Expression, 1962-1985 (Box 92, Folder 111 - 113)
    - Toward a General Theory of the First Amendment
      - Correspondence, 1963-1976, undated (Box 92, Folder 114)
      - Drafts, Undated (Box 92, Folder 115 - 117)
      - Italian translation, 1979-1982 (Box 92, Folder 118)
      - Japanese edition, 1970-1972, undated (Box 92, Folder 119 - 120)
      - Reprints and comments, 1963-1980, undated (Box 93, Folder 121 - 122)
      - Research, Undated (Box 93, Folder 123 - 125)
      - Reviews, 1966-1982 (Box 93, Folder 126 - 127)
      - Sales, 1967-1972 (Box 93, Folder 128)
    - Young Lawyer for the New Deal [book drafts]
      - Front matter, chapters 1-5, 1985-1987, undated (Box 93, Folder 129 - 137)
      - Chapters 6-15, 1985-1987, undated (Box 94, Folder 138 - 149)
      - Chapters 16-17, 1985-1987, undated (Box 95, Folder 150 - 152)
- Course Materials, 1946-1983; Series IV
  Arranged alphabetically by course name, the series consists of lecture notes, bibliographies, and outlines from courses Thomas Emerson taught at Yale Law School. The series also includes correspondence between Emerson and some of his students regarding JSD (doctor of science of law) theses and individual studies.
  - Administrative Law, 1950 (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Process, 1946-1975, undated (Box 96, Folder 2 - 9)
  - Conspiracy Law and Individual Rights, 1970 (Box 97, Folder 10 - 11)
  - Constitutional Law, 1948-1976 (Box 97, Folder 12 - 21)
  - Correspondence
    - JSD theses, 1960-1976 (Box 97, Folder 22)
    - Senior studies/individual work, 1956-1983 (Box 98, Folder 23 - 24)
  - Devices for Community Participation, 1969-1972, undated (Box 98, Folder 25 - 30)
  - Introduction to Public Law
    - 1948-1949 (Box 98, Folder 31 - 39)
    - 1949-1955 (Box 99, Folder 40 - 50)
    - Bibliographies, assignments, general, 1947-1976, undated (Box 99, Folder 51 - 53)
  - Labor Law, 1955 (Box 100, Folder 54)
  - Legislative Process, 1947-1976, undated (Box 100, Folder 55 - 61)
  - Mobilization Controls, 1952 (Box 100, Folder 62)
  - Modern Social Legislation, 1953-1963 (Box 100, Folder 63)
  - Political and Civil Rights
    - Assignments, outlines, 1947-1980 (Box 101, Folder 64 - 65)
    - Class notes, 1958-1976 (Box 101, Folder 66 - 73)
  - Political Justice Seminar, 1970-1971 (Box 102, Folder 74 - 79)
  - Political Justice Workshop, 1970-1976 (Box 102, Folder 80)
  - Public Law Division, 1961-1965 (Box 102, Folder 81)
  - Seminar on Individual Rights, 1958 (Box 102, Folder 82)